Finding Aid for the Riichi Ashizawa papers, 1899-1965 (bulk 1906-1945) LSC.2010.03
UCLA Library Special Collections
Riichi Ashizawa papers
1899-1965
1906-1945
UCLA Library Special Collections
Ashizawa, Riichi
LSC.2010.03
0.25 Linear Feet (1 half document box and 1 oversize box)
Riichi Ashizawa (also known as George Asher) was a photographer and entrepreneur in San Francisco, California. Ashizawa was a Yamanashi native who came to the United States in 1899. He ran businesses such as Yamato Laundry, Asher's Picture House, Asher's Art Shoppe, and Ho-Bi-Do. The collection includes biographical essays written by Ashizawa and photographs (with selected negatives) that he took for the Japanese American communities in the San Francisco area. Photocopies of documents and photographs of his businesses are also included.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ashizawa family
Gift of Clifford I. Uyeda, April 3, 1965.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942303363606533
Biography/History
Issei immigrant, photographer and entrepreneur Riichi Ashizawa (?????) was born in Yamanashi Prefecture in 1882, the second son in his family. He arrived in San Francisco in 1899. In 1901, he became the owner of Yamato Laundry and later Golden Gate Laundry. In 1906, after experiencing the San Francisco earthquake, Ashizawa moved to Chicago, Denver and then Philadelphia. He studied art, chemistry and dyeing textiles during this period. In 1915, Ashizawa returned to San Francisco and worked as a photographer for a Japanese daily newspapers, the Shinsekai Shimbun (formerly Hokubei Mainichi News) and Nichibei-jiji (formerly Nichibei Times). In 1916, Ashizawa started a roving photography business by installing a darkroom in his car, a 1912 Studebaker, and he photographed people and scenery in the Golden Gate Park area. Ashizawa opened an antique and artistic picture framing shop, Asher's Art Shoppe on Sutter Street in 1920. In the same year, he married Susie Suzuki (????) from Yokohama, Japan and later had a son Roy and a daughter Sumiko. During World War II, Ashizawa and his family were incarcerated in the Topaz Relocation Center, also known as the Central Utah Relocation Center, near Delta, Utah. Ashizawa worked as a police officer in the Relocation Center. After the war, Ashizawa resumed his business at Ho-Bi-Do (???) on Polk Street.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of autobiographical essays, documents and photographs by Riichi Ashizawa (George Asher), related to Yamato Laundry, Golden Gate Laundry, Asher's Picture House, and Asher's Art Shoppe in San Francisco, California. Ashizawa photographed for the Japanese daily newspapers, Shinsekai Shimbun and Nishibei-jiji and documented the local Japanese group activities such as undo-kai or athletic activities, picnics, arrival of picture brides and so forth. The collection also includes acetate negatives, glass plate negatives, photocopies of business records and correspondence. The photographs, which were taken in San Francisco, Placerville and Los Angeles, California date from approximately 1899 to 1920.
Related Material
Japanese American Research Project Collection of Material about Japanese in the United States (Collection 2010). Available at Library Special Collections, UCLA.
Photographers -- California -- San Francisco -- Archives.; Photographs.; Japanese Americans -- California -- San Francisco -- Archives.; Japanese American Research Project (University of California, Los Angeles); Ashizawa, Riichi, 1882- --Archives.
- Autobiographical sketches in Japanese., 1965 (Box 42, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  ??????Omoide no mama [As I recall], 16 double leaves.
  ???????? = Ashizawa Riichi hachijusan sai; George Richii Ashizawa Age 83 San Francisco, California 2/65, 15 double leaves.
  Issei oral history interview written out San Francisco 3/65, 21 double leaves.
- Photographs., 1899-1920 (Box 42, Folder 2)
  The Ashizawa brothers (from left to right): Riichi, elder brother, Ryohei, younger brother, Buichi. ca.1899.
  Fresno farmer and his family came from Hawaii. 1904.
  Wagons and bicycles of Mr. K Saruwatari. 1905.
  Front view of Yamato Laundry. 1905 March
  New Year's party of Yamato Laundry. 1906.
  San Francisco market, Ferran Building and Emporium Department store after the earthquake. 1906 April 18.
  Earthquake rescue center house of Consul Uyeno on Pine and Gouth, wagon belonging to Yamato Laundry to transport emergency foods. 1906 April 19.
  After the fire from the earthquake at the site of Yamato Laundry and Ashizawa and Buichi. 1906 April 20.
  Employees from Golden Rule Laundry and Yamato Laundry after the earthquake. 1906 May.
  The Queen City Dye Works in Denver where Ashizawa studied dyeing and cleaning work. 1907 February.
  Philadelphia Textile where Ashizawa studied art, dyeing and chemistry. 1908 September.
  Group of entertainers wearing kimono and costumes at a picnic. 1908 (glass plate negative see box 152, folder 1).
  The view of wholesale produce market organized by Issei entrepreneurs at the 9th street Los Angeles market. 1911 October 7.
  Group of Japanese dressed for shibai or stage performance. 1915 (glass plate negative see box 152, folder 4).
  Two ladies from inaka [country-side] to a picnic holding cameras. 1915 (glass plate negative see box 152, folder 2).
  Ryohei Ashizawa (from left to right), elder brother; Dr. Tsuchiya, personal physician to Emperor Taisho and Buichi Ashizawa, younger brother standing by a Willy's Knight model 1910 at Laguna Honda. 1915 (glass plate negative see box 152, folder 3).
  Consul Oyama, Mr.&Mrs. ??? Abiko, Mr.&Mrs. ??Uryu at Panama exhibition in San Francisco. 1915.
  At Okei's grave site, the owner of the land, Louis Veerkamp holding the Tanto dagger given by the first Japanese group farming immigrants, Wakamatsu Colony in Placerville, standing with Japanese visitors. ca. 1915.
  Undokai [athletic day] by Nihonjinkai audience surround the performer in a distance at Southwest side of Masonic-Anza Street. 1916 (glass plate negative see box 152, folder 4).
  Naniwabushi performance by Naramura at the Masonic-Anza baseball ground (stadium). ca.1916 (glass plate negative see box 152, folder 5).
  Wrestlers at sumo tournament waiting for their turn at Masonic-Anza picnic ground. 1916.
  Sumo wrestling tournament. 1916 (glass plate negative see box 152, folder 6).
  Photographic darkroom on Studebaker chassis. 1916.
  Woman performing with shamisen players at Undokai (athletic day) by Nihonjin-kai at Southeast side of Masonic-Anza. 1916 (glass plate negative see box 152, folder 7).
  Picture brides just arrived aboard Shunyo Maru in San Francisco port. 1919 (glass plate negative see box 152, folder 8).
  A naginata instructor Kaoru Makabe. 1920.
  Asher's Art Shoppe at 1205 Sutter Street, San Francisco. 1920
- Photocopies of business correspondence and records of Asher's Picture House, Asher's Art Shoppe and his activities during World War II., 1901-1961 (Box 42, Folder 3)
  Photocopies of photo of five young men (Riichi Ashizawa on further right at age 18) in front of the Golden Rule Laundry at 1040 Larkin Street, San Francisco. 1901.
  Driver's license. 1918 April 19.
  Registration with Local Board. 1918 September 12.
  Certificate of business under fictitious name Asher's Picture House. 1923.
  Registration documents of Asher's Art Shoppe. 1923 May 23.
  Permission for Ashizawa to drive his truck into Topaz Relocation Center to secure culinary water for Drum mountain mine. 1943 August 21.
  Certificate to confirm George R. Ashizawa as foreman of Japanese workers at the Dowd Manganese mine at Drum Mountain. 1943 August 25.
  War Relocation Authority notice of assignment as police officer at $16.00 per month at the Central Utah Relocation Center. 1945 January 2.
  Bill of sales receipt from Topaz Consumer Cooperative Enterprises. 1945 March 23.
  Letter of recommendation of Ashizawa's mending skills on antiques to Mr. C. Palmer Woodbury of the Japan Centre New York City. 1951 March 5.
  Letter of appreciation from Eleanor M. Muller, Nassau Tavern hotel in Princeton, New Jersey. 1953 November 23.
  News clipping of Ashizawa's roving photography business at Golden Gate Park in 1916, published in The Pony Express. 1953 December vol. XX page 7.
  Letter of appreciation from Lorne M. Stanley. 1954 February 26.
  Post card invitation from Consul of General of Japan of San Francisco Masao Yagi honoring Ashizawa for his contribution to the U.S. - Japan relationship on the occasion of ?????????[100 Years of Japanese-American Amity]. 1960 June 14.
  Mrs. Helen Ekerold's notes for her newspaper article "Bits and Pieces Together Again" on Ashizawa and his antique shop ??? Hobido. 1961.
- Photo negatives., 1915-1920 (Box 42, Folder 4)
  ?????? Admiral Uryu (center) at Japanese Tea Garden in San Francisco. 1915.
  Japanese group picnic in San Francisco. ca. 1919.
  Group picture of ?????????Kashuu kaki shijoo kabushiki kai [California Japanese flower market stock holder association] 25th anniversary celebration UndokaiUndokai. 1920 June 20.
- Group of Japanese dressed for shibai or stage performance., 1915 (Box 42, Folder 5)
  Glass plate negative, for photographic print see box 42, folder 2
- News clipping of Ashizawa's 1919 roving photography business on Studebaker chassis published in 1953. (Box 42, Folder 6)
  Photocopy in folder 3
- Group of entertainers wearing kimono and costumes at a picnic., 1908 (Box 152, Folder 1)
- Two ladies from inaka (country-side) to a picnic., 1915 (Box 152, Folder 2)
- Ryohei Ashizawa, elder brother of Ashizawa, Dr. Tsuchiya, a personal physician to Emperor Taisho and Ashizawa's younger brother, Buichi Ashizawa standing by a Willy's Knight model 1910 at Laguna Honda., 1915 (Box 152, Folder 3)
- Undokai by Nihonjin-kai audience surround the performer in a distance., 1916 (Box 152, Folder 4)
- Sumo wrestling tournament., 1916 (Box 152, Folder 5)
- Woman performing with shamisen players at undokai by Nihonjin-kai in San Francisco., 1916 (Box 152, Folder 6)
- Naniwabushi performance by Naramura at the Masonic-Anza baseball ground (stadium)., ca. 1916 (Box 152, Folder 7)
- Picture brides just arrived aboard Shunyo Maru in San Francisco port., 1919 (Box 152, Folder 8)
- The ship Shunyo-maru arrived in San Francisco Port carrying picture brides., 1920 (Box 152, Folder 9)